Susan B. Anthony Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Susan B. Anthony Papers1846-1934 (bulk 1846-1906)
MSS11049
Anthony, Susan B. (Susan Brownell), 1820-1906
500 items 7 containers 3 linear feet 7 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Reformer and suffragist. Correspondence, diaries, daybook, speeches, scrapbooks, and miscellaneous papers relating primarily to Anthony's writings, lectures, and other efforts on behalf of women's suffrage and women's rights. Includes material pertaining to the National Woman Suffrage Association, after 1890 the National American Woman Suffrage Association, and to the New York State Woman Suffrage Association.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Anthony, Mary S. Mary S. Anthony papers.; Anthony, Susan B. (Susan Brownell), 1820-1906.; Avery, Rachel Foster, 1858-1919.; Bloomer, Amelia Jenks, 1818-1894.; Johnson, Adelaide, 1859-1955.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865--Assassination.; Mott, Lucretia, 1793-1880.; Phillips, Wendell, 1811-1884.; Pillsbury, Parker, 1809-1898.; Shaw, Anna Howard, 1847-1919.; Stanton, Elizabeth Cady, 1815-1902.; Stone, Lucy, 1818-1893.
Organizations
American Anti-Slavery Society.; National American Woman Suffrage Association.; National Woman Suffrage Association (U.S.); New York State Woman Suffrage Association.
Subjects
African Americans--Suffrage.; Antislavery movements.; Slavery.; Social problems.; Temperance.; Women's rights.; Women--Education.; Women--Suffrage.
Occupations
Reformers.; Suffragists.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Susan B. Anthony, reformer and suffragist, were given to the Library of Congress primarily by Lucy E. Anthony, Ann Anthony Bacon, and others from 1940 to 1964. An addition to the collection includes items received by the Library through gift and purchase in 1987 and 1990.
Transfers
A photograph of Anthony, given to the Library in 1988, has been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where it is identified as a part of these papers.
The Library's Rare Book and Special Collections Division has custody of Susan B. Anthony's personal library. Among the more than 250 volumes are thirty-four scrapbooks compiled by Anthony, some of which were transferred from the Manuscript Division together with related printed matter and newspaper clippings. The scrapbooks are available on seven reels of microfilm for purchase or loan through the Microform Reading Room.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Susan B. Anthony are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of these papers is available on seven reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1820, Feb. 15 Born near Adams, Mass.
1837-1838 Student, Friends seminary near Philadelphia, Pa.
1839 Teacher, Eunice Kenyon's Friends Seminary, New Rochelle, N.Y.
1846 Headmistress, Female Department, Canajoharie Academy, Rochester, N.Y.
1848 Joined the Daughters of Temperance in Canajorarie, N.Y.; by Mar. 1849 had become Presiding Sister of the Montgomery Union, No. 29, of the Daughters of Temperance in Canajoharie, a position she also held after moving to Rochester, N.Y., and joining that city's union in mid-1849
1849 Managed family farm
1851 Met Elizabeth Cady Stanton
1852 Formed the Woman's New York State Temperance Society
1853 Helped organize the “Whole World's Temperance Convention” Helped a group of Rochester, N.Y., seamstresses draft a code of fair wages for working women in the city
1854 Organized and participated in a canvass to obtain signatures on petitions demanding woman suffrage and improvement of the Married Woman's Property Law in New York
1856 Principal New York agent, American Anti-Slavery Society
1866 Corresponding secretary, American Equal Rights Association
1868-1870 Published the Revolution, a weekly periodical edited by Elizabeth Cady Stanton and others
1869 Organized a woman's suffrage convention, Washington, D.C. Formed, with Elizabeth Cady Stanton, the National Woman Suffrage Association
1872 Voted illegally for president
1876 Presented a “Woman's Declaration of 1876” with two colleagues at the Centennial Exposition, Philadelphia, Pa.
1881-1902 Financed and coedited first four volumes of
History of Woman Suffrage (New York, Fowler & Wells, 1881-[1922] 6 vols.)
1888 Founded the International Council of Women
1890 Settled in Rochester, N.Y. Vice president at large, National American Woman Suffrage Association
1892-1900 President, National American Woman Suffrage Association
1892 Trustee, State Industrial School, Rochester, N.Y.
1895-1896 Campaigned in California to secure the vote for women
1898 Collaborated in the preparation of
The Life and Work of Susan B. Anthony (Indianapolis, Bowen-Merrill Co., 1898-1908. 3 vols.), by Ida H. Harper
1900 Helped open the University of Rochester, N.Y., to women
1904 Founded, with Carrie Chapman Catt, the International Woman Suffrage Alliance
1906, Mar. 13 Died, Rochester, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Susan Brownell Anthony (1820-1906) span the period from 1846 to 1934, although the bulk of the material dates from 1846 to 1906. The papers include correspondence, a daybook, diaries, scrapbooks, speeches, and miscellaneous items.
A volume of correspondence is dated 1846-1905 and consists primarily of Anthony's letters to Rachel Foster Avery concerning the details of Anthony's extensive lecture circuit, her finances, the activities of the National Woman Suffrage Association, and her work on the multivolume History of Woman Suffrage which she coedited with Elizabeth Cady Stanton and others. The file also includes several letters from Anthony to the Reverend Anna Howard Shaw and letters from Wendell Phillips. Although most letters concern suffrage, a few deal with personal and family matters.
A daybook, 1856-1860, records the financial account Anthony kept of her work for the American Anti-Slavery Society, woman's rights, and personal expenditures for postage, room and board, travel, advertising, rent for lecture halls, and other items. Twenty-five volumes of diaries span the period from 1865 to 1906 with some gaps and omissions. For the most part, the diaries contain brief notations of Anthony's activities and a financial record kept in the back of each volume. Other topics noted in the diaries include family matters, African-American and woman suffrage, lecture tours, and important events of the day, such as Lincoln's assassination. Among her associates mentioned in the diaries are Amelia Jenks Bloomer,; Lucretia Mott,; Parker Pillsbury,; Elizabeth Cady Stanton, and Lucy Stone.
Six scrapbooks assembled by her sister, Mary S. Anthony, contain clippings from newspapers published in all parts of the United States with a heavy concentration of those from New York state and Washington, D.C. Memorabilia for the period 1876-1934 is also included. The scrapbooks primarily document the activities of Susan B. and Mary S. Anthony in behalf of woman suffrage, especially the conventions of the National Woman Suffrage Association and the New York State Woman Suffrage Association. The scrapbooks also contain biographical articles on Anthony and her associates in the suffrage movement and articles on women in higher education and professional employment, particularly in law, medicine, and journalism.
Manuscripts of speeches and other writings complete the collection. Anthony's early focus was temperance and abolition as well as women's suffrage and education. The manuscripts date from her first public address in 1848 to 1895 when she was presented with part one of Elizabeth Cady Stanton's
The Woman's Bible (New York, European Pub. Co., 1895-1898).
Two letters were added to the collection in 1997. A photocopy of a letter dated 1883 from Anthony to Mary Kimball Rogers concerns a speech she thought had been lost in Omaha, Nebraska. A typed letter dated 1896 from Anthony to Adelaide Johnson concerns the charges of illegality that were raised when Johnson's marriage ceremony was performed by a woman. Anthony's lobbying effort to have statues placed in the United States Capitol of herself, Stanton, and Mott as the founders of the woman suffrage movement is also noted in her letter to Johnson.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in five series:
Correspondence, 1846-1905
Daybook and Diaries, 1856-1906
Scrapbooks, 1876-1934
Speeches and Writings, 1848-1895
Addition, 1883-1896
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm78011049
Container List
- Correspondence, 1846-1905 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  Letters to and from Anthony.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Bound volume (Box 1, Reel 1)
- Daybook and Diaries, 1856-1906 (Box 2-3, Reel 1-4)
  One daybook and twenty-five diaries.
  - Daybook, 1856-1860 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - Diaries
    - 1865, 1870-1874, 1876-1878, 1883, 1888, (11 vols.) (Box 2, Reel 1-2)
    - 1890 (Box 2, Reel 3)
    - 1892-1901, 1903-1904, 1906, (13 vols.) (Box 3, Reel 3-4)
- Scrapbooks, 1876-1934 (Box 4-6, Reel 5-6)
  Six volumes and two folders of clippings and memorabilia.
  - 1876-1903 (Box 4, Reel 5)
  - 1892-1902 (Box 5, Reel 5)
  - 1902-1903 (Box 5, Reel 6)
  - 1905-1906, (3 vols.) (Box 6, Reel 6)
  - Clippings, 1890-1934 (Box 7, Reel 6)
  - National American Woman Suffrage Association Convention programs, 1905-1906
- Speeches and Writings, 1848-1895 (Box 7, Reel 6-7)
  Speeches by Anthony. Also includes The Woman's Bible, part one, by Elizabeth Cady Stanton.
  - List of speeches (Box 7, Reel 6)
  - 1848, first public address
  - 1852, speech delivered at Batavia, N.Y., in company with Emily Clark (2 copies)
  - 1852, The Church and the Liquor Traffic
  - 1853
    - Apr. 17, Maine Law
    - June 27, Expediency (Box 7, Reel 7)
  - 1856, Report on Educating the Sexes Together, written by Elizabeth Cady Stanton and delivered by Anthony at the New York State Teachers Convention, Troy, N.Y.
  - 1858, speech, Union Agricultural Society, Yates County Fair, Dundee, N.Y.
  - undated 1859, Make the Slave's Case Our Own
  - 1861
    - The No Union with Slave-holders Campaign
    - What Is American Slavery?
    - Judge Taney
  - 1862, speech on emancipation
  - 1877, Homes of Single Women
  - 1895, The Woman's Bible (part 1) by Elizabeth Cady Stanton
- Addition, 1883-1896 (Box 7)
  Two letters by Anthony.
  - Letters, 1883, 1896 (Box 7)